

SR. SOFTWARE ENGINEER · ANDROID EXPERT

7/A, Kashmeri Tola Lane, Azimpur, Dhaka

□ (+880) 1685 053007 | Spn.ahmed92@gmail.com | Sopan-ahmed.web.app | Sopan Ahmed | Sopan-ahmed-abaa8714a

"Love for all, Hatred for none."



## **Summary**

Software engineer with 7.5+ years of experience. Working as an Android developer since 2015, and enjoy collaborating with the different product areas: scrum, refinement, UI/UX. I have extensive work experience on Mobile Application Development, Development Planning, Wireframing, Agile Development, and Team Lead. Have a passion for code craftsmanship and design. Love to make great products specially which impact on people's everyday life.

I value the following aspects from a company and role:

- Make things simple for challenging projects.
- Great values, teammates and room to mentor my peers.
- Next-generation technologies and their impact on software as a service.
- Growth opportunities, career plan, feedback, and goals.
- Focus on the customer/end-users satisfaction, and quality assurance.
- Data-driven decision making, analysis of metrics, and monitoring product usage in production.

# **Areas of Expertise**

- Mobile Technologies: Android SDK, ADB, DDMS, SQLite, Notification Services including Push, Location Based Services, Content Provider, Various System Services, Broadcast Receiver amp; Services, RESTful Web Services, HTTP, JSON, IntentService, AsyncTask, Fragments, Maps
- Third Party Libraries: Socket.io, Volley, RetroFit, gson, okhttp, dagger, Glide, butterknife, exoplayer, Picasso.
- Cloud API: OAuth, Facebook, Twitter, Firebase Auth
- Programming: Java, Rx Java, Kotlin, XML(parsing DOM, SAX, Pull), HTML5, SQL, JSON, Multithreading, JavaScript
- Tools: Android Studio, JIRA, Git, Github
- Operating Systems: Windows, Linux
- Database: NoSQL, Firestore, Room, Realm, MySQL Queries, PL/SQL Stored Procedures, Functions, Triggers

# Work Experience\_

#### Mobile Apps Team, ACI Ltd.

SR. SOFTWARE ENGINEER (ANDROID)

Tejgaon, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct. 2017 - Present

- Worked as part of a team to completely organize and architect the two Educational Android App to implement a newer UI and improved performance.
- Project management using Jira, scrum and Agile methodologies & contributed to full life cycle development of applications.
- Establishes and/or co-ordinates programmers of work (delivered through development)
- Individually implemented multiple new features including 'Push Notifications', 'media player', 'quiz', 'Java game development and more.
- Solely responsible for integrating different libraries, implementing use of API end points, localization of strings and more.
- · Implemented several API microservices in Node.js, socket.io and Java Animation based logical games.
- · Learnt new OOP language called Kotlin on the fly and successfully migrated parts of the project to Kotlin.
- Worked on more than 50 projects & responsible for resolving bugs, production and QA issues.

#### Nobo IT Mirpur, Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER & PROJECT MANAGER (ANDROID+WEB), PART TIME

Jan. 2018 - Dec. 2021

- As the only android developer for the company, very quickly jumped on-board and took full responsibility of the development and operation
  of the app.
- Performed bug fixes on existing code and analyzed existing code to proactively detect and fix code. Performed an extensive code review to better understand the entire code.
- Developed 10+ different kinds of projects including Property Search, Educational & Ecommerce app
- Responsible for resolving bugs, production and QA issues.

## **TiCON System Ltd**

Uttara, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Nov. 2016 - Sep. 2017

SR. SOFTWARE ENGINEER (ANDROID)

- Took bottom line responsibility for push notifications, using Javascripts to integrate with the Android app.
- Designed and developed background jobs to run at regular intervals to send alerts to users who have downloaded the app but not made any progress in 'n' number of days.
- · Implemented the receiver and extracted JSON messages from Push notifications to direct it to the target activity.
- Developed Audio-Video streaming app named Willfon, Miruphone & others.
- Single-handed design and implementation of Admin module.

ANDROID ENGINEER Jul. 2016 - Nov. 2016

- · Worked individually as well as part of a larger team on developing and maintaining multiple client applications.
- Worked on multiple emulators to thoroughly develop and test deployment and interoperability on multiple platforms.
- Developed more than 15 projects including Car buy-sell app named Peepep.

Multiplexer Lab Agargaon, Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER (ANDROID, BACK END)

- Developed app doctor-patient consultant & social photo-sharing app
- Implemented overall Android application logic and wrote API server for community service, along with project lead engineer.

#### **Emporium Technology Ltd.**

Dhanmondi, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Dec. 2015 - Jun. 2016

Junior Software Engineer Jan. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- Developed a game like flappy bird using Java
- · Developed app like company profile, all newspaper reader & more
- · Assist in budget for internal hardware/software along with Sr. Developer, create/manage architecture diagrams/plans

# **Projects**

Medhabir Supernova Client: ACI Ltd

**EDUCATIONAL AND LEARNING APPLICATION** 

Nov. 2019 - Ongoing

- Medhabir Supernova is the Educational and learning application that aims to help the secondary (Class 6-10) level students in Bangladesh to enhance and develop their knowledge.
- It offers 325 instructional animated videos, chapter-wise pdf, beautifully highlighted summary, and other learning contents. Several exercises, exams, model tests and quiz will increase proficiency in every subject.
- The app will be published soon.

Kids Brain Builder Client: ACI Ltd

**EDUCATIONAL AND LEARNING APPLICATION** 

Jun. 2021 - Ongoing

- · Kids Brain Builder is the Educational and learning application that aims to help the kids to enhance and develop their basic knowledge.
- It offers 200 animated videos, 100 logical games, and other learning contents.
- The app will be published soon.

Waseka Client: UK

PROPERTY SEARCH APPLICATION

Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2021

- Search residential, commercial properties for sale, letting agents in your area or by name across the UK
- Compare house prices with waseka's house prices
- Play store link: Waseka

### Ahmadiyya Bangla Prokashona

ISLAMIC EDUCATIONAL APPLICATION

Client: MKA Bangladesh

Feb. 2022 - Aug. 2022

• Learn islamic education throug quran and other pdf books & load web content through trusted web

Play store link: Ahmadiyya Bangla Prokashona

# **Strengths**

- Stick to Delivering Results Identify the problems that cause them distress, and recognize their own existing problem-solving skills. Relying on a mix of problem-solving and time-management skills.
- Open to think, Creative Skills Use creative thinking and resourcefulness to come up with the most optimal and original ideas. Always keep in mind the limitation of personal capabilities to implement the ideas.
- Life-long Learner, love to learn new technologies Never done learning and always seeking to improve myself. Curious about new possibilities and taking action to explore them.

## **Education**

### **Shahjalal University of Science and Technology**

(Affiliated College: Sylhet Engineering College)

Sylhet, Bangladesh

B.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Apr. 2010 - Dec. 2014

• GPA 3.70 out of 4.00

Participate 2 university-level programming & hackathons as part of the official 3-person team in 2011 and 2014